Guide to the American Slavery Documents Collection, 1757-1924 and undated RL.11093
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
American slavery documents collection
1757-1924 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
RL.11093
2.0 Linear Feet 2 boxes; 1 oversize folder
Collection of manuscript items relating to American slavery assembled over a number of decades by the staff of the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library at Duke University. Collection contains items documenting the sales, escapes, and emancipations of enslaved people from colonial times through the Civil War, and to a lesser extent, materials relating to slavery in the United States dating from the post-emancipation period.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically. Undated items are listed last.
Biographical / Historical
Slavery was a widespread practice in colonial and Revolutionary America. Most enslaved people in the United States were descended from Africans who were forced into slavery and brought to America against their will. The system of American chattel slavery meant that any children of enslaved people would also be enslaved, automatically at birth. Importation of enslaved people from outside the country was federally prohibited in 1808, but the domestic slave trade remained very active in the United States throughout the early nineteenth century. Although all Northern states had abolished slavery by the 1800s, slavery was actively practiced in Southern and Western states, causing deep political, religious, and economic divides that eventually led to the American Civil War. The 1863 Emancipation Proclamation by Abraham Lincoln freed enslaved people in rebel territories; this was followed by the Thirteenth Amendment in 1865 outlawing slavery throughout the entire United States.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The American Slavery Documents Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as gifts and purchases from the 1930s through 2020. It was formerly known as the African-American Miscellany Collection.
Collection Overview
The collection brings to light details of the lives and deaths of enslaved and free Africans and African Americans in the southern United States, primarily in North Carolina, Virginia, and Kentucky, but also in Alabama, Georgia, Louisiana, Maryland, Mississippi, New York, South Carolina, and Tennessee. There are also six albumen studio portrait photographs, mounted on card stock, dating from the second half of the 19th century, along with a copper token from the American Colonization Society, dated 1833.
Items have been foldered individually, with the inventory reflecting their titles, geographic origin, and date (if known).
African Americans -- History -- 19th century; African Americans -- History -- 1863-1877; African Americans -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- North Carolina; African Americans -- Social conditions -- 19th century; Antislavery movements -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Free African Americans -- United States -- Social conditions -- 19th century; Free African Americans -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Fugitive slaves -- United States -- History -- 19th century; Slavery -- United States -- History; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
- Slavery Series, 1757-1867; undated; 1
  - Bill of sale, Court of Common Plea, Court at Camden, 1757 April - November (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Bill of sale for one slave: Bett, 8 year old girl; sold by Lawrence Lancaster to Thomas Cook for £32, 10 shillings, 1757 March 18 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Bill of sale for an enslaved person, Leander, from N.C. Trowbridge to E.H. Simmons, 1757 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Scope and Contents
    Bill of sale for "seven hundred dollars in full for one negro boy named Leander" from N.C. Trowbridge to E.H. Simmons.
  - Bill of sale for one slave girl: 11 y.o., 32 pounds and 10 shillings, from Absalom Lancaster to Thomas Cook, 1760 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bill of sale for one slave, from Aroh Currison to Thomas Cook, N.C., 1771 April 17 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Bill of sale for three slaves: Toby, James, and Jacob, from Zachariah Flurry to James Prown, S.C., 1779 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Bill of sale for multiple slaves,, from Dan Heyer, S.C., 1779 April 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bill of sale for one slave: Hal, from William Merrit to Rob Long, Chatham County N.C., 1780 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bill of sale for one slave woman: Catey, 60 pounds and 18 shillings, from Abiyah Holbrook to Samuel Boykin, 1787 April 2 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bill of sale for one slave: Glasgow, 48 pounds currency, 1794 April 7 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Import/Export document for two bales of blankets, imported by Thomas Shaw, New Orleans, 1794 October 14 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bond payment slip for 325 pounds to Robert Pasley, 1794 October 21 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Import document for 50 casks of claret, imported by John Vaughn from Bourdenaux, bound for Port au Prince, 1794 December 9 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Bill of sale for one slave boy, 70 pounds currency, from William Plummer to Robert Jones of Warren County, Franklin County N.C., 1796 March 30 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Emancipation of Edmund, son of Page, a mulatto woman, former property of deceased, Peter Marks, Albemarle County, Va., 1796 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Emancipation of Evelin[e?] Lewis, daughter of Jenny, a mulatto woman, former property of deceased, Peter Marks, Albemarle County, Va., 1796 April 5 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - John C. Town of Fredrickburg: Neptune York certified born free (about 37 years old, 5 ft. 11 inches); recorded with court September, 1803, Albemarle County, Va., 1798 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Bill of sale for three slaves: one woman, Vilet; one girl, two years, Cheney; one boy, four years, [G?]ack, Cumberland County, N.C., 1799 August 20 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Emancipation of Cato, a man about 65 years old, and Cloe, a woman about 65 years old, freed by John Hudson's will and testament, John Nicholas, Albemarle Co., Va., 1800 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Bond/Account information sheet, owner received a sum of 1000 pounds from W. Fitzpatrick, 1800 April 24 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Register of Negroes and Free People of Color, Rustburg, Va. (oversize), 1801-1850 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Record of emancipation of female, Frankey, by John Nicholas, Albemarle Co., Va., 1801 July 6 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Indenture, 1802 January 22 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Bill of sale for two slaves: Mary and her daughter Eliza, to Henry Dana Ward, S.C., Northern Circuit, 1802 February 2 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Bill of sale for one slave boy, $350, to James Parrant, 1805 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Bill of sale for two slave boys, $520, 1805 June 24 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Two bills of sale transactions on one leaf, for Harriet, aged 20, and her daughter Elizabeth, aged 6 months, $280; and Delilah, $213, to George Legg., Baltimore, Md., 1805 October 11 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - A note proclaiming freedom, John Walker: Nancy Gardiner, a mulatto girl, age 20, born free to a free mother, Albamarle Co., Ala., 1806 November 20 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Account balancing slip of paper, 1807 February 17 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Decree of gift of five slaves: Phill, woman, Luckey, young woman, Nanny, young woman, Allen, small boy, and Harry, small boy, from Col. John Hamilton of Norfolk, Va. to Mrs. Patey Brickall and her three children, 1808 December 27 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Bill of sale for one slave woman, $400, Tenn., 1809 April (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Bill of sale for one slave boy: Abraham, 90 pounds, from Daniel Jackson Manea to John Kelly, Granville County, N.C., 1809 May 6 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Bill of sale for one slave girl, $287, from David Hensler and William Maxwell of Rockingham District N.C. to Hardy Clemmond of Pendleton District, S.C., 1810 June 4 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Bill of sale for one slave woman: Serena, and her child, $440, from M. Stokes to Samuel Guy, 1810 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Bill of sale for one slave girl, $350, to Samuel Grey, 1811 March 1 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Certifications of the freedom of seven men: Thomas Pritchard, Scipio Melden, William Anthony, James De Hart, Henry Tafe, Joshua Bornish, John Roberts, Court of Common Plea, 5th Ward, New York, NY, 1811-1814; 7 items (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Slip of paper: "Thomas Thomson", 1811 May 2 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Bill of sale for one slave man: Dave, 27 y.o., $400, to William Sutton, 1812 January 23 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Bill of sale for one slave: Hannah, from William Brumfield to Richard Jones, 1812 November 18 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Bill of sale for tract of land and two slaves: Harriet, girl, and Tanney, woman, from Mr. Maybanch, Liberty County, Ga., 1812 December 9 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Copybook (17 pages) belonging to Mary Hamlins of Salem, Ohio; includes practice scripts, arithmetic, and a poem, The Blood Brother, in support of abolition, 1812-1817 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Bill of sale for one slave boy: Henry, 14 y.o., $300, from William Bennett to Richard Jones, Pittsylvania County, Va., 1813 August 6 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Bill of sale for one slave woman: Sue, $300, to Mr. Ballins, 1813 December 9 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Empancipation of slave woman and daughter: Sue and Margaret, from Elizabeth Graham, Georgetown District, S.C.; also gives the former slaves $50 from her estate, 1815 September 27 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Bill of sale for two slaves: woman Amy, 27 y.o. and her child Sidney, 8 m.o., $400, from Joseph and Margaret Lawrence to Samuel Guy, 1817 May 12 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Bill of sale for one slave girl: Esther, 20 y.o., $1500, from William Astin of Va. to Samuel Grey, 1818 February 18 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Bill of sale for one slave: Daniel, from Millie Allen to Robert Park, 1818 November 8 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - List of assets, including slaves, of Adam Corraths, 1821 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Paper certifying that the children of Moses and Marian, named Susan, Israel and Rachel, were free, 1822 January 14 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Bill of sale for one slave woman: Bell, 24 y.o., $550, from Kenneth Clarke to John Bethan, Moore County, Md., 1822 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Bill of sale for one slave boy: Bedford, $309, from Mark Weatherly to Martin Weatherly, N.C., 1822 October 17 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Bill of sale for slaves, $597.92, from John Cawley, S.C., 1823 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Bill of sale for one slave woman: Jenny, $300, from Edmund Hoskins to Joseph Blount, N.C., 1823 April 29 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Bill of sale for four slaves: Milly, 2 y.o., Ann, 5 y.o., Jack, 2 y.o., and Mary, 8 m.o., $777, from James and Josiah Huie to Samuel Guy, 1824 March 31 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Bill of sale for one slave, $251, to Sam Woods, 1824 October 23 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Bill of sale for one slave man: Dave, 35 y.o., $325, to Samuel Guy, 1824 November (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Bill of sale for one slave girl: Beck, 14 y.o., $300, to Samuel Guy, 1824 November 15 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Letter discussing the author's a visit from the author's brother, Richard, and the freeing slaves to Martha Moore of N.C., 1825 June 14 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Trust deed between William Scott, Richard Wallace, and John Pilson in which Scott gives Wallace slaves as collateral: Phyllis, woman, her child Robert Wilson, and two slave men, Jesse and Ben, 1827 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Bill of sale for one slave: Ben, 9 y.o., $200, 1827 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Bill of sale for three slaves: Jimmy, Milton, and Carter, from Peter Winn to William Ryan of Guilford County, N.C., 1827 December 22 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Bill of sale for one slave girl: 19 y.o., from Alexander Hogan to Samuel Guy, 1828 February 9 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Bill of sale for two slave boys: Richard and Benjamin, $1200, 1828 July (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Bill of sale for one slave woman, $550, from J.K. Shelton to Richard Jones, Pittslyvania County, 1828 September 27 (Box 1, Folder 62)
  - Emancipation note of slave John Brown, from Isaac Bett, Md., 1829 January 16 (Box 1, Folder 63)
  - Document certifying the freedom of Elias, Frederick County, Md., 1829 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 64)
  - Bill of sale for one slave boy: Adam, $200, from John Mae Bullers of Johnston County to Gilbert Multon, Richmond County, N.C., 1829 May 14 (Box 1, Folder 65)
  - Notes to the Caroline County Jailer asking him to take slaves into custody, slaves named: Adam, Randal, Walker, Jim, and Eldrid, 1829 July 16 - 1830 January 4; 6 items (Box 1, Folder 66)
  - Bill of sale for four slaves: Milly, Jim, 7 y.o., Eliza, 4 y.o., and Isaac, 18 m.o., to Gilbert Mae Millan, Richmond County, Fayetteville, N.C., 1829 August 21 (Box 1, Folder 67)
  - Notice announcing a slave sale to be held at Pittsylvania Courthouse [Va.?], 1830 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 68)
  - Document certifying the freedom of Matthew Scroggins, 28 y.o., 5 ft. 5 in., Frederick County, Md., 1830 April 16 (Box 1, Folder 69)
  - Document certifying the freedom of Solomon, Frederick County, Md., 1830 September 2 (Box 1, Folder 70)
  - Paper from Thomas Berry detailing two bills of sale proclaiming that "William Williams, a colored man," wanted to purchase his wife and child from Berry, 1831 February 28 (Box 1, Folder 71)
  - Bill of sale for one slave: Dianah, $250, from Benjamin Grandstaff to Mr. Rice, Shenandoah County, Va., 1831 April 19 (Box 1, Folder 72)
  - Bill of sale for one slave: Henry, 18 y.o., $450, from Morgan Davis to James Bistand of Adam County, Miss., 1832 January 4 (Box 1, Folder 73)
  - Document certifying the freedom of Betsy, Frederick County, Md., 1832 May 7 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Court proceedings from Nelson County, Va., 1832 September 24 (Box 1, Folder 75)
  - Bond of indemnity to the Captain of the barque "Hercules," a ship that took S.C. and Ga. "colored persons" from Savannah to Liberia., 1832 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 76)
  - Ship manifest for the schooner "Dekalb" of "Negroes, Mulattoes, and Persons of Color," District of Baltimore, Port of Baltimore, 1835 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 77)
  - Response to John Hunt about his notice of selling 60 slaves, New Orleans, 1835 September 1 (Box 1, Folder 78)
  - Bill of sale for two slaves: James Ross's document notarized by Maria Cohen; free black woman sells Eve's children; sale of two slaves for $500 to Levi S. D'tyon - slaves: Nancy, age 8, and John, age 6, 1836 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Statement of the slaves belonging to heirs of John L. Ward, Richard Ward to Martha A. Power, an heir, 1838 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 80)
  - Bill of sale for two slave women, $1200, from Cole to Farmer, Halifax County [N.C.? Va.?], 1838 (Box 1, Folder 81)
  - Bill of sale for one slave man: Philip, $400, S.C., 1839 June 13 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Note for rental of slave man for one year from S. and N. Buck: Bill, including furnishing with winter clothing, shoes, stockings and blanket, $97.50, to Joseph Snapp, Front Royal area, Va., 1840 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Bill of sale for one slave boy: Ralph, 16 y.o., $650, to Nancy Robards, N.C., 1840 February 8 (Box 1, Folder 84)
  - Bill of sale for one slave: Sheriff's Bill of Sale - sale of Warren, negro boy, about seven years of age for $202; buyer: Mrs. Hannah L., [B], South Carolina, 1840 November 2 (Box 1, Folder 85)
  - Bill of sale for one mulatto man: Lewis, $800, from public auction to Franklin Mores, Sheriff's Office, Sumter District, S.C., 1841 November 1 (Box 1, Folder 86)
  - Bill of sale for one slave man: Jim, 26 y.o., $500, to William Mitchell, Ga., 1843 July 7 (Box 1, Folder 87)
  - Three bills of sale (2 Ky., 1 S.C.), 1852-1865 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Return of property notice for six slaves: Mariah, Hester, Adam, Sarah, Sigga, and Jane, to Paul H. Allen, 1844 (Box 1, Folder 88)
  - Mortgage of personal property (S.C.), 1843 October 14 (Oversize-folder 1)
  - Bill of sale for one slave man: Jacob, $187.50, to Richard Jones, 1844 October (Box 1, Folder 89)
  - Note for rental of a slave woman from James R. Richards (executor? of the will of William Hopewells) for one year: Henrietta, including furnishing with winter clothing, shoes, and blanket, $27.50, to [J. I] Trout, Front Royal area, Va., 1844 December 27 (Box 1, Folder 90)
  - Bill of sale for one slave and blacksmith tools: Ben, blacksmith, from John Ing to Bryant Young, 1845 March 12 (Box 1, Folder 91)
  - Bill of sale for one slave girl: Caroline, 22 y.o., $401, from public auction to Richard R. Winfrey, Hall County, Ga., 1846 December 1 (Box 1, Folder 92)
  - Bill of sale for one slave woman: Matilda, and her two children, $550, from Peter Griggs, 1847 December 8 (Box 1, Folder 93)
  - Payments, Mr. C. Pettejohn, 1848 February 29-October 29 (Box 1, Folder 94)
  - Paper detailing four bills of sale, 1843-1849 (Box 1, Folder 95)
  - Bill of sale for one slave boy: George, 11 y.o., $450, to Emmanuel George, 1849 (Box 1, Folder 96)
  - Affidavit certifying the freedom of a mulatto woman, 42 y.o., saying the woman was born free, written by M. Hugh Owens, Frederick County, Md., 1849 January 15 (Box 1, Folder 97)
  - Bill of sale for one slave woman and her two children, $812, to William B. Enecks, Barnwell District, S.C., 1849 May 11 (Box 1, Folder 98)
  - Check for one slave: Davy, $485, written by C.H. Simmons, 1849 July 5 (Box 1, Folder 99)
  - Bill of sale for one slave woman, $600, from Richard Jones to Janus Pointer, Pittsylvania County, Va., 1849 October 3 (Box 1, Folder 100)
  - Bill of sale for one slave: Susan, $575, from E. Bellin to E.H. Simmons, 1849 December 21 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Bill of sale for four slaves: George, Lucy, Louisa, and Piemus, $1600, from Freeman Hoyt to E.H. Simmons, Charleston, S.C., 1849 December 22 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Documents pertaining to the sale of one slave: Jenny, $618, from James M. Fitts to Henry E. Solomons, Beaufort District, Charleston, S.C., 1850 March 4; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Documents pertaining to the Will of Martin Weatherly: heirs deciding his estate, mentions slaves, Francis, Viney and her son Aaron, 1850 April 1; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Bill of sale for one slave boy: Aron, 10 y.o., $457.50, from Erwin Hurmer to Jacob Coble, 1850 September 28 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bill of sale for one slave girl: Sally, 11 y.o., $450, from Hall and Johnson to Richard Jones, 1850 October 3 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Auction notes and prizes, New Orleans, 1851 March 14 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Arrest warrant for slave Isaac for actions on board steamboat Mary Washington, including assaults and threats made against Warren Moudowney, Corporation of Fredericksburg, 1851 July 25 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Bill of sale for one slave woman and her two children: Sally: 24 y.o., Lear, 2 y. and 10 m.o., and Deanah, 9 m.o., $1005, to Paul D. Felder, Orangeburgh District, S.C., 1852 August 14 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Transfer of slaves Viney and her daughter of 18 mos., Adelia, from Hezakiah and Sarah Thompson to their daughter, Adelaide Kemp, St. Helen's Parish, La., 1853 June 29 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Bill of sale for one slave girl: Mariah, 14 y.o., $200, from Emanuel Geiger to Alexander Forsyth, selling because of "falling fits", 1853 August 6 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Note for rental of slave woman for one year from [Schew's] McKay: Maria, including furnishing with winter clothing, shoes, stockings, bonnet, and blanket, $36, to [name excised], Front Royal area, Va., 1853 December 27 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Details of will of Thomas John, deceased on 1849 May 3, Warren County, Ky. Owned slaves: George, Richard, Catherine, Louisa, and Martha, states that they should be freed 15 yr. after his death. Includes a purchase agreement for Martha, $350, for sale to Ma, 1855 January 1 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Bills of sale from the executor's sale of the estate of Charles E. Clark: Clarissa and her two children, Eliza and unamed infant; Matilda and her child, Fanny, 1855 December 13; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Bill of sale for one slave girl: Jenny, 12 y.o., $700, to Alfred Carson, 1856 February 15 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bill of sale for two slaves: Emilie, 18 y.o., and Eve, 3 y.o., $1000, from Lucien Monteguet to Nathaniel Williamson, New Orleans, 1856 August 2 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Bill of sale for three slaves: Kitty, woman, 22 y.o., Kirt, boy, 3 y.o., and Burt, boy, 10 m.o., $1600, from Mahala F. Bowie to Hugh McDonald, Miss., 1857 January 25 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Bill of sale for one slave woman: Sukey, 45 y.o., $400, from Thomas Bradshaw, Alamance County, N.C., 1857 February 2 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Bill of sale for one slave boy: Mel, $730, from Sheriff's Office to G.M. Tusen, Beaufort District, S.C., 1857 February 2 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Notes on slaves received from A. Bland's will by his two heirs, George and Albert: Young Peter, Butter, Jo, Rose, Charlotte, Young Isaac, Irvin, Harriet, Amy, Pink Jerry, Mary, Old Peter, Augusta, Isaac, Sneky, Victoria, Anderson, Charles, Pliant, Bill, He, 1857 February 12; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Bill of sale for one slave boy, Henry, 9 years, $400, from Jacob Semly to G. Davidson, 1857 April 30 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Bill of sale for Lucy, enslaved woman about 22 years old, from R. W. Walker to J. L. McFall, Jefferson, Cass County, Texas, 1857 June 16 (Box 2, Folder 102)
    Bill of sale includes notation that Walker guaranteed Lucy to "be sound in mind and body excepting an injury that she secured in and about the private parts in consequence of an abortion."
  - Bill of sale for one slave boy, Grandison, from M.C. Manning, 1857 August 8 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Indenture to hire man, Peter, for year 1858, from Samuel Williams to J. White, 1857 December 26 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Note for rental of slave woman for one year from Ann H. Millar: Lucinda, including furnishing with shirts, dresses, petticoats, stockings, aprons, shoes, and blanket, $50, to Isaac Trout, Front Royal area, Va., 1858 December 28 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Bill of sale for two slave women, from John Hunter to J. E. Calhoun, Grand Gulf, 1858 February 8 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Bill of sale for two slave women: Jane and her child, from Smith Hubbard to John Hunter, 1858 March 2 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Bill of sale for one slave girl: Mary, from James S. Miller to John M. Carson, Alexander County, N.C., 1859 December 30 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Bill of sale for one slave woman and her four children: Susan, 30 y.o., Mary, 10 y.o., Vivey, 6 y.o., and Julia, 3 y.o., from S.S. Tompkins to John S. Smyley, 1859 March 11 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Life insurance policies for two slaves: Nancy and Margaret, taken out by E.L. McNair of S.C., Chesterfield County, S.C., 1859 June 7; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Bill of sale for three slaves: Mary, 28 y.o., and two children, from D.G. Crawford, 1859 October 13 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Letter from John Brown, prison inmate, to Mrs. George L. Strens of Boss [Boston?], Mass., 1859 November 29 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Letter on relative prices of men, women, and children, from Dickinson Hill and Co., Richmond, [Va.?], 1860 January 4 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Auctioneer's letter, from Pulliam and Co., Richmond, [Va.?], 1860 January 15 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Bill of sale for two girls named Jane and Polly aged 12 and 13. Dated February 4, 1860., 1860 February 4 (Box 2, Folder 101)
  - Bill of sale for one slave: Susan, from John S. Seabrook to P.S. Felder, Charleston, 1860 March 7 (Box 2, Folder 34)